<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>geospatial big data management | Isam Al Jawarneh</title>
    <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/tag/geospatial-big-data-management/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/tag/geospatial-big-data-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>geospatial big data management</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Isam Al Jawarneh</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 21:42:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/media/icon_hud73ee2a58f6e166f5506c1763554804d_135107_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>geospatial big data management</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/tag/geospatial-big-data-management/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ApproxSSPS</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/spatialapprox/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 21:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/spatialapprox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ApproxSSPS&lt;/code&gt; ia a system for approximate processing of geo-referenced mobility data, at scale with quality of service guarantees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It specifically focuses on stateful aggregations (e.g., means, counts) and top-N queries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, it features a controller that interactively learns the latency statistics and calculates proper sampling rates to meet latency or/and accuracy targets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An overarching trait of &lt;code&gt;ApproxSSPS&lt;/code&gt; is its ability to strike a plausible balance between latency and accuracy targets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We evaluate &lt;code&gt;ApproxSSPS&lt;/code&gt; on Apache Spark Structured Streaming with real mobility data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We also compared &lt;code&gt;ApproxSSPS&lt;/code&gt; against a state-of-the-art online adaptive processing system.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our extensive experiments prove that &lt;code&gt;ApproxSSPS&lt;/code&gt; can fulfill latency and accuracy targets with varying sets of parameter configurations and load intensities (i.e., transient peaks in data loads versus slow ar-riving streams).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Moreover, our results show that ApproxSSPS outperforms the baseline counterpart by significant magnitudes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In short, &lt;code&gt;ApproxSSPS&lt;/code&gt; is a novel spatial data stream processing system that can deliver real accurate results in a timely manner, by dynamically specifying the limits on data samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;publication:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/sensors2021/&#34;&gt;MDPI Sensors 2021&lt;/a&gt;  (journal impact factor (indexed in &lt;em&gt;ISI Thomson Reuters&lt;/em&gt;): 3.576)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SpatialSPE</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/spatialspe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 21:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/spatialspe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;SpatialSPE&lt;/code&gt; accepts a continuous query and QoS budgets (expressed as latency and accuracy targets) and employs our spatial-aware sampling method (that we dub as SAOS, which is an integral part of &lt;code&gt;SpatialSPE&lt;/code&gt;) to select an appropriate sample,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;then it computes an approximate answer and serves it to the user incrementally, together with rigorous error bounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have implemented &lt;code&gt;SpatialSPE&lt;/code&gt; on top of Spark Structured Streaming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;publication:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2020/&#34;&gt;IEEE CAMAD2020&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/globecom2019/&#34;&gt;IEEE GLOBECOM2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MeteoMobil</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/meteomobil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 21:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/meteomobil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recent research is focusing extensively on building Cloud-based open-source solutions for big geospatial data analytics in the Cloud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avalanches of georeferenced mobility (human, vehicles, etc.,) and micro-blogging data (e.g., tweets) are being collected and processed daily.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, mobility data alone is not enough to unleash the opportunities for insightful analytics that may assist in mitigating the adverse effects of climate change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, answering complex queries such as follows: “what are the Top-3 neighborhoods (districts, boroughs, etc.,) in Buenos Aires in Argentina in terms of vehicle mobility where the index of Particulate Matters (PM10) air-borne pollutant is greater than 40”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similar queries are necessary for emergent health-aware smart city policies.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, they can provide insights to municipality administrators so that they foster the design of future city infrastructure plans that feature citizen health as a priority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, by restricting the number of vehicles accessing highly-polluted areas of the city during peak hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, such information can be used to build mobile interactive maps for daily dwellers so that to inform them which routes to avoid passing-through during specific hours of a day to avoid being subjected to high-levels of vehicle-caused air-borne pollutants (such as PM10).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, answering such a query would require joining real-time mobility and environment (e.g., meteorological) data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stock versions of the current Cloud-based open-source geospatial management systems do not include intrinsic solutions for such scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;MeteoMobil&lt;/code&gt; is a system for the combined analytics of integrated information representing mobility and environment conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have implemented our system atop Apache Spark for efficient operation over the Cloud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have tested the system and shown its capabilities in supporting climate change analytics.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our results show that MeteoMobil can be efficiently exploited for advanced climate change analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;publication:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;presented at IEEE CAMAD 2021, To Appear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficiently Integrating Mobility and Environment Data for Climate Change Analytics</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 18:29:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>QoS-Aware Approximate Query Processing for Smart Cities Spatial Data Streams</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/sensors2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 21:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/sensors2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to export or download the citations.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button to check out the example.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/IsamAljawarneh/ApproximateStream&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Locality-Preserving Spatial Partitioning for Geo Big Data Analytics in Main Memory Frameworks</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/globecom2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 18:18:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/globecom2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficient QoS-Aware Spatial Join Processing for Scalable NoSQL Storage Frameworks</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/ieeetransactions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 19:23:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/ieeetransactions/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatially Representative Online Big Data Sampling for Smart Cities</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 18:29:58 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Spatial Data Management for the Internet of Things: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 19:27:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/survey/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial-aware approximate big data stream processing</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/globecom2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2019 22:29:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/globecom2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SpatialSSJP</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/spatialssjp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 21:42:21 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/project/spatialssjp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;SpatialSSJP&lt;/code&gt; is a QoS-aware adaptive stream-static &lt;code&gt;join processor&lt;/code&gt; that exploits a custom &lt;code&gt;geospatial online sampling&lt;/code&gt; method for selecting proportionate sampling fraction through the application of an embedded rate controller and serve it to SAOS using a &lt;code&gt;feedback loop mechanism&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SpatialSSJP is an &lt;code&gt;approximation&lt;/code&gt; framework that is designed to efficiently tradeoff miniscule error-bounded accuracy for low-latency, thereby assisting SpatialDSMS to survive during brutal burst spikes in data arrival rates.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SpatialSSJP achieves that in a &lt;code&gt;circadian rhythm&lt;/code&gt; without counteracting the benifits of its controller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;publication:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Manuscript submitted to an IEEE Transactions journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In-memory spatial-aware framework for processing proximity-alike queries in big spatial data</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 22:29:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/camad2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cost-effective strategies for provisioning NoSQL storage services in support for industry 4.0</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/iscc2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2018 22:29:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/iscc2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficient spark-based framework for big geospatial data query processing and analysis</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/iscc2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2017 22:29:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/iscc2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic identification of participatory mobile health communities</title>
      <link>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/dynamic-identification/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 22:29:31 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://IsamAljawarneh.github.io/publication/dynamic-identification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
